[music]
Father God,
I ask that
I'd be able to teach well today.
And, God, I hope that
you would help Mars Hill
to be a place where hurting
people are served.
And I pray, Lord God,
for those who will hear
this sermon,
some helping them along
a journey toward healing,
and those who will start
a journey of healing,
but with the first steps
being incredibly painful.
God, I thank you for my wife's
bravery in writing
the seventh chapter
of the "Real Marriage" book,
and I thank you that I have
the great honor of teaching
that content today,
and I thank you, Lord,
that she is a great gift
that you've given to me.
And so, God I pray
that this time
would be focused on
helping others
and that you would allow
me to finish this sermon.
Amen.
This is the one sermon
I never wanted to preach.
Grace and I were
sitting on a couch.
It was late one night,
just hanging out,
and we--just visiting,
nothing particularly deep.
And I started asking her a few
questions about some issues
in her past
and experiences that she'd had,
and she just answered
them matter-of-factly,
just very casually,
very unemotionally,
and I just started bawling.
And she was taken aback.
She couldn't understand
why I was emotional.
I don't get emotional
very often.
Almost always, if I do, it's
because women and children
are in danger.
And she said,
"Oh, I'm so sorry."
I said, "No, don't be sorry.
"You didn't do anything wrong.
"You didn't say anything wrong,
but you're
a sexual assault victim."
And she's like, "What me?
What are you talking about?"
I said, "Yeah, what you just
explained was
textbook sexual assault."
And all of a sudden, everything
in our marriage and relationship
made sense.
We had been married,
at that point, for--
gosh, it was 6 years ago.
This year, we'll celebrate
our 20th wedding anniversary.
So, we were married at
that point, maybe 13-14 years.
And we dated for
4 1/2 years before we married,
so we'd been together
17 or 18 years.
I mean, I'd known Grace
since high school,
and we were good friends.
And now I knew her.
I knew everything.
And she hadn't
concealed anything,
so she wasn't ever
dishonest with me.
She just never saw
it for what it was.
And I think that's pretty common
with victims not only of
sexual assault, but of
other kinds of assault, as well,
that sometimes you tend to
be more clear perspective seeing
someone else's life, but
you interpret the data
in your own life differently.
And sometimes
there'll be repressed memory,
where you don't remember
certain things,
and then something will
trigger it, or disassociation,
which is a clinical term, where
somebody who's being assaulted
in some particular
way, they'll disassociate.
They'll sort of mentally check
out, just as a coping mechanism.
And sometimes people are
just not emotionally ready
to remember and deal
with certain trauma or trouble.
And I believe that God doesn't
give us more than we can bear,
and for those who come to
understand some things
that have been done to them,
sometimes it
is because they're finally
at a place in their maturity
in Christ that they could,
they could handle it.
And so, in some regards,
I guess it's an encouragement,
meaning we're finally
ready to deal with this.
Well, it was one
of those moments,
where I knew
what had happened to my wife,
and . . .
and it was devastating.
And--because for me,
I'm like a lot of you men,
I'm a defender, protector.
Like, the safety of my wife and
kids is the highest priority,
and to realize that I wasn't
there until 17--and some things
happened to her before 17,
before I'd met her--
it really bothered me that
I wasn't there to protect her.
It still does.
And so we started reading,
and talking, and praying,
and trying to figure out,
"What do we do now?"
I had Grace start journaling out
all of the related experiences
in her life, because she'd
never really thought about it.
She'd have a thought
here or a grief moment there,
but the business of life
would just sort of compel her
to proceed forward.
So, I said, "Honey, I really
need you to take
a couple of days."
And I put her
in a safe, quiet hotel
and stayed in contact with her,
but I took care of the kids
and took care of the house
and said, "Honey, I just need
you to focus
"and journal this out, and think
this out, and pray this out,
so we get an idea of what
exactly we're dealing with."
Because she'd never really given
herself time to process
and to grieve.
And then we started studying
and looking for ways to work out
what had happened to her.
And we met a couple of times
with a biblical counselor.
"Okay, what do we
need to do, not do?
"What's a good course
of action for us, so I can love,
and serve, and help my wife?"
And in the grace of God,
some years later--
I mean, our friendship is great.
Our marriage is
really fantastic.
It kind of was a revealing
moment at Christmas,
when, with the kids,
we were all in a circle,
and we were talking and praying,
and I asked each of the kids,
"What are you most
thankful for?"
And my oldest daughter,
she smiled and she said,
"I'm thankful that you and Mom
are never going to get divorced,
because you're best friends."
And that's where we're at.
That being said, when
it came time to write
the "Real Marriage" book, she really
wanted to help people,
and she really loves people,
and she's very brave,
and she wanted to
basically say, "If I'm honest,
"then other people
can be honest,
"and if this has happened to
other people,
I want to help them and
encourage them to get help."
And so her motives are
very good and very, very pure,
and I really appreciate
her courage.
So, the subject matter for
this sermon is going to be
the content that she wrote,
and I'll start by
doing something
that I think is important, and
that is defining sexual assault.
It comes from this book,
"Rid of My Disgrace"
by Justin and Lindsey Holcomb.
He's a pastor here
at Mars Hill
and runs Resurgence for us.
His wife, Lindsey,
is also a leader in the church.
She's a deacon, and she was a
rape crisis clinic case manager,
and he taught women's studies
at the University of Virginia
and is a specialist in sexual
assault and domestic violence.
And Grace and I actually
asked them to write this book,
because we wanted to have, from
our church, a good Bible-based,
Jesus-focused resource to help
people who have been
sexually assaulted.
And we love that book,
and, you know, endorsed it,
and all of that, and are really
honored that that comes from
Mars Hill Church.
And their definition is,
"Any type of sexual behavior
"or contact where consent is not
freely given or obtained
"and is accomplished through
force, intimidation, violence,
coercion, manipulation,
threat--"
hold it right there, guys--
"deception,
or abuse of authority."
So, that's what
we're talking about.
It's very important, because it
used to be that the word "rape"
was used a lot, and it still
is, but this is a larger, legal,
clinical definition, and it's
important that as you look at
your life, or your spouse,
or people you know and love,
that you understand
what has happened
and have the right language.
We don't want to falsely
accuse anyone; at the same time,
we don't want to
falsely excuse anyone.
And it manifests
itself in three ways.
"The 'acts' can be physical,
verbal, or psychological."
In the age
of bullying and the Internet,
in the age of certain
inappropriate speech
and conduct, it just, it can be
physical contact
that connotes sexual assault,
but it doesn't
necessarily have to be.
It also can be verbal
and/or psychological.
And some of you will ask,
"Man, a whole sermon on this?
"Why is this necessary?
"I've been to a lot of churches,
and I've not heard them
talk about this."
I would say, I love them,
but that's their failure.
I was talking with
a very well-known pastor of
a decent-sized church,
and he asked this question
some years ago of me.
He asked, "Why do you guys talk
about sexual assault so much
in your church?"
Well, part of it is
it's my wife's story.
Part of it is, as you'll
see in a moment, it's epidemic.
I said, "Well, isn't it
an issue in your church?"
And at the time, I think
he had 800 people.
He said, "Well, I know of
two or three women who have been
sexually assaulted, but it's
not a big issue at our church."
I said,
"You've not done your homework.
"You don't know your people.
"You are ignoring a problem
and assuming there isn't one.
"That means you have a culture
in which the people
"can't be honest about what has
been happening to them
and get the help
that they need."
I said, "So, it's not
that you don't have a problem;
it's that you're
ignorant of a crisis."
And, really, that's the issue,
that sexual assault
is an epidemic.
It's one in four women.
How many women do you know?
One in four.
Statistically, the younger
they are, the more likely it is.
It's also true for
one in six men,
and men are highly unlikely to
report it for reasons
of shame and embarrassment,
and so it's not just women.
Ten to fourteen percent of wives
are assaulted by their husbands,
which means
some women are not only victims;
they're married to their abuser,
which is a situation
I would liken to torment.
Abuse is what happens
when something is done to you,
but you escape.
Torment is where it
keeps happening to you,
and you're trapped.
For some women,
marriage is torment.
They live with their abuser.
And it wasn't actually until
the '70s that the laws
even began to recognize
marital sexual assault,
that it was even a crime
for a man to abuse his wife.
Assault is also more common in
cohabitation than in marriage.
And some of you say, "That's
why I don't want to get married.
I just want to live
with my boyfriend."
A boyfriend is far more likely
to sexually assault a girlfriend
than a husband is
to assault a wife.
And here's
the staggering statistic.
Only 5-40% of cases
are ever actually reported.
Grace's would be an example.
It's never been reported,
not criminally speaking.
So, you look at
the underreporting.
Well, statistically, what that
means is a large percentage
of women and men,
who call Mars Hill Church home,
have been sexually assaulted.
What that means is
if it's not part of your story,
it is part of the story
of someone you know.
I mean,
how many women do you know?
How many men do you know?
How many do you know closely,
and intimately, and personally?
Well, statistically,
you know a lot of victims,
and you probably don't
know that they're victims,
because sometimes they don't
have the language to understand
what has happened to them,
or the shame has caused them
not to really talk about that.
And so at Mars Hill Church,
we want to be a place where
it's safe for people to be
honest about what has happened,
so that they can get hope,
and help, and healing
through Jesus and his people.
It's a big part of what we do.
And I'll just say
this practically.
I see it undergirding
lots of issues.
When we deal with people
that have drug problems,
alcohol problems,
sexual addiction problems,
major depression problems,
not always, but oftentimes,
an underlying cause is
a past sexual assault.
It's amazing how this epidemic
manifests itself
in other kinds of suffering.
Now, what happens to those who
are assault victims--
and this can be sexual
assault, physical assault,
various kinds of abuse--what
tends to happen is they have,
oftentimes, basically,
an identity crisis, like,
"Who am I?"
And so Grace rightly
communicates in the chapter
that there are
four masks that they will wear,
and this is an identity
that they assume.
And like an actor or an actress
reading a script and playing
a role, they will try to cope
with what's happened to them
by acting out in one
of these four ways.
The first is a good person.
And the underlying
logic is, basically,
"Something very bad happened
to me, but I'm a good person.
"They're a bad person.
I'm a good person.
"They did a bad thing,
so I'm going to do good things.
I'm a good person."
These people tend to show
up early to work, stay late,
work hard, super faithful,
volunteer for everything,
absolutely dependable,
sometimes very organized,
because it's
an issue of control.
They felt like much of
their life was out of control,
and they want to keep as much
of it as possible
under their control.
These are people
who are moral, they're obedient,
they're compliant, they're
dependable, they're reliable.
They're good people outwardly.
It's not bad to be good,
but the motive is bad
for them being good.
They're trying to show,
"I'm a good person,
and what happened
didn't affect how good I am."
Sometimes it's the people
who volunteer the most,
and give the most, and serve the
most that are hurting the most,
and they're hiding.
Number two,
there's the religious person.
These people make everything
incredibly, overtly spiritual.
These are the people
that it's always
out-of-context Bible verses.
They'll talk about
Satan and demons
and the sovereignty of God,
and "he's going to
work it all out,"
and "when he closes a door,
he opens a window,"
and "greater is he who
is in you than he who is
in the world," and "I'm more
than a conqueror in Christ."
And you ask them,
"How are you doing?"
They'll say, "God works out all
things for the good of those
who love him."
It's like, "You didn't
even answer my question.
"You're using theology
as a fig leaf to hide behind.
"I can't even know you.
I know what you think;
I don't know who you are."
And sometimes they mean well,
and sometimes they love
the Lord, but they just,
they just don't know what to do.
And sometimes it's even an
error in the way the gospel is
presented, because sometimes the
gospel is presented solely as,
"If you sin, Jesus died.
Tell him your sin.
He'll forgive you."
True, but what about, not
just the sins you've committed,
but the sins that
have been committed against you?
What do you do with those?
You can't pray,
"Dear God, please forgive me
for being raped,"
because you didn't do anything.
You're the victim, not
the perpetrator of the offense.
But some people
become incredibly religious,
and I would say some
of the most devoutly religious,
hyper-spiritual people
that Grace and I have ever dealt
with, as we get to know
them, they've been assaulted,
and they've
not really worked that through.
There's the party person.
One gal in a tragic counseling
appointment early on
in my ministry articulated
it most devastatingly.
I still pray for her often and
recently bumped into someone
who knows her, and she's
not walking with Jesus,
but people are still talking
to her over a decade later.
She was an assault victim
and a young woman,
probably early 20s,
if memory serves me correct,
and I was meeting with her.
She was just doing some really
outrageous things
that were very dangerous.
And I remember asking her,
I said, "Why do you do this?"
And she looked at me,
and she said, quote,
"I'm a dirty girl,
so I do dirty things."
That's what her
grandfather made her say,
when he would leave
her room at night.
And she decided that that
would be her identity,
so she would be
the life of the party.
She's gregarious, hilarious.
She's fun to be around.
She's got
the best sense of humor ever,
but everything's a joke, and
she's always ready to just put
a drink in her hand and let
her be the center of attention.
And it's not a sin
to have a good sense of humor,
and it's not a sin to go out
and, you know,
enjoy people and their company,
but for her, it's tragic.
Some of you are like that.
Everything is a joke.
You start talking about personal
things, change the subject,
throw out a punch line.
"Ah, let's go do something fun.
Why are you so serious?"
Number four, there's
the tough person,
and the tough person
has learned,
"Somebody got close to
me and really hurt me.
I'm going to make sure
nobody ever gets close again."
They could be physically
intimidating.
They can be emotionally
They can be verbally
intimidating, like,
"You keep your distance."
Sometimes,
they're just cold and aloof.
You know, like, "Man,
I don't even know that person.
They don't open up at all."
Other times, there's
an aura about them, like,
"Don't get too close."
If you start to impose
in any way
that they feel uncomfortable,
you are going to pay.
How about you?
For those of you
who are assault victims
of various sorts and kinds,
you know, what mask do you
wear? What role do you play?
What identity have you assumed?
And when it comes
to our identity,
our identity
determines our testimony.
Who we think we are determines,
really, how we live.
And there's
really only three options.
There's what I've done,
what they've done,
or what [God's] done.
"If it's what I've done,
well, then I'm going to try
"to be a good person or
a religious person,
and I'm going to try and
make myself a better person."
If it's what they've done,
"I'm going to be a party
person or a tough person.
"Well, I'm damaged goods.
I may as well have fun," or
"I was hurt once,
but I'll protect myself
from here on out."
Your identity comes
either from what you've done,
what they've done,
or what [God's] done.
So, how does Jesus
play into all of this?
At this point,
we don't have good news, right?
You need some good news.
So far, all we've got is news.
And I want to tell you
three things related to Jesus,
and that is, number one,
that Jesus forgives all sin.
So, some of you
are going to hear this,
and you're going to say,
"I'm not the victim.
I'm the sinner."
Or maybe you're both.
Maybe, "Something was done to me,
and then I turned around and did
something to someone else,"
or "Something was done to me,
and I've just been
bitter ever since."
What do you do with that?
1 John 1:7-8,
"If we walk in the light--"
and this is about openness,
and honesty, and authenticity,
which requires a lot of humility
to say, "Okay, here's who I am.
Here's what I've done."
It's being honest
and transparent.
And one of the reasons I admire
Grace so much for writing
the chapter in the book and
being honest about her story
is she's walking in the light.
She's saying,
"Here's what happened."
And in so doing, she's inviting
other people to do the same.
And it's been pretty remarkable.
The feedback we've gotten
has generally been,
particularly on this
issue, super encouraging.
It says,
"If we walk in the light,
"as he is in the light,
we have fellowship
with one another."
As people are honest, they get
closer, as opposed to faking it,
playing roles,
hiding behind fig leaves.
As you're honest and say,
"Here's what I've done,
and here's what's
been done to me--"
and you do this
with your spouse,
you don't necessarily
do--you don't do this with
strangers, or dangerous
people, or your abuser,
but you do this with
your spouse, or your parent,
or a biblical counselor,
or a godly church leader,
or a trustworthy friend.
You have fellowship.
You feel closer.
It's been
really interesting this week.
Emotionally, this has been
a pretty shipwrecked week for me
for a whole lot of reasons,
but all leading up
to having to teach--or
getting to teach this content.
But I've had multiple women
walk up to me in stores,
in coffee shops, look me in
the eye, start crying and say,
"Tell Grace,
'Thank you for chapter 7.'"
And they feel
a fellowship with her.
One was a young woman who said,
you know, "That's my story,
"and Grace told hers and
got help, so I'm telling mine,
so I can get help."
Well, praise God for that.
And so as we talk about sin
we've committed and sin
that's been committed against
us, we walk in the light.
We have fellowship
with one another.
We actually build relationships.
We get beyond the,
"How are you doing?"
"Great.
How are you?"
"Great."
"Well, we're both great.
Glad that's over with.
Have a nice life."
One of the guys on
the film crew,
before the sermon, he asked,
"How are you doing?"
I said, "I'm not going to
lie to you, not well."
He was like, "I understand."
"If we walk in the light,
as he is in the light,
"we have fellowship
with one another,
and the blood of Jesus his
Son cleanses us from--"
how much sin?
"All sin."
"If we say we
have no sin--"
"Oh, I've not done
anything too bad,
and nobody's done
anything bad to me."
"We deceive ourselves."
You can actually
start to believe that lie.
"Nothing bad's happened to me,
and I haven't done anything
"real bad to them, so, you know,
thankfully, it's not a big deal.
"Our life is pretty easy.
"Move along with the needy
people, who've got big issues,
because ours is pretty simple."
We deceive ourselves.
Satan, in the Bible,
is called a deceiver.
People can deceive
themselves, as well.
"And the truth is not in us."
We're not telling the truth.
So, when it comes
to the sin we've committed,
and the sin that's
been committed against us,
we need to be truthful about
all of it, not diminish it.
People like
to partially confess their sin,
or they like to partially
confess sin
that's been committed
against them, because of shame.
They don't want to
tell the whole truth.
But God asks us
to tell the whole truth,
so that we can deal with reality
and not be self-deceived.
And the key is that, "The blood
of Jesus his Son cleanses us
from all sin."
And the idea here is this,
that because of the sins
we've committed,
we all deserve death and hell.
And I know it's not
popular to say that,
and there's a lot of
places that'll tell you,
"You're basically a good person,
and don't really worry about it.
God loves everybody.
You're going to be fine."
Let me tell you this.
Everybody is a bad person
and headed toward hell
at breakneck speed.
Hell is the active wrath
of a just and holy God
against evil.
And I praise God that he doesn't
look at this earth
and all of the injustice,
tyranny, oppression, rape,
assault, and neglect, and say,
"Those are some good people."
I'm glad that God
looks at it, as a father would,
toward children that
were being assaulted and says,
"That really grieves
and angers me,
"and I cannot tolerate
that forever.
It will come to an end."
Some of you are in grave danger.
You are headed toward hell.
You are living
in the path of the wrath of God.
And the good news is
that God comes as Jesus Christ.
God comes as a man.
He lives as we do,
yet without any sin,
and he substitutes
himself on the cross,
and he suffers and dies
in our place for our sins,
so that at the cross of
Jesus, justice and mercy kiss,
and our sin is paid
for through the blood of Jesus,
through the blood of Jesus.
So, friends, let me say this.
There will be
justice for us all.
It's either at the cross
of Jesus or in hell,
and no one
is getting away with anything.
And for those of you who are
victims of assault and abuse
of various sorts and kinds,
in forgiving someone,
you're not saying it's okay.
What you're saying is you'll
leave it in the hands of God.
You'll leave it
in the hands of God.
And that is either
Jesus died for it,
or they will die and go
to hell for it. But either way,
it will be dealt with.
And we're all sinners
by nature and choice,
and we need to know that our
sin is such a big deal
that it required
the death of God.
So, it's a great travesty
for even a victim to say,
"Yes, what happened
to me did, in fact, occur,
but it wasn't that
big of a deal."
Yes, it was.
God had to die for it.
That's how big of a deal it is.
But Jesus can
and does forgive all sin.
It doesn't matter
what you've done.
Jesus can and does
forgive all sin,
even the horrific sins of sexual
assault; yes, even toward women;
yes, even toward children.
He doesn't just forgive people;
he changes them
so that they stop sinning
and start serving.
Do you know Jesus?
Is your sin forgiven,
or are you living in the path
of the wrath of God?
But Jesus does forgive all sin.
But we need to talk about it.
You need to talk
to God about it.
That's that word,
"We walk in the light."
It's being honest with God,
it's being honest with others;
and if you're married, it's
being honest with your spouse.
Who are you,
and what have you done?
Number two,
Jesus takes all shame.
One of my great frustrations
with gospel presentations is
that it is said,
"You're a sinner,
"and if you repent of
sin and trust in Jesus,
he will save you."
That's absolutely true, but what
happens to those who are not
just the sinners, but
the victims of others' sin?
What do you do?
What do you do when you're
the one who was beaten,
when you were
the one who was betrayed,
the one who was molested,
when you were
the one who was raped?
What do you do?
You don't repent of your sin.
You're the victim of sin.
You didn't sin.
You were the victim of sin.
What do you do?
And that is that Jesus
not only forgives sinners;
he cleanses victims.
And what he does,
he takes their shame.
Because you know
what sin produces?
Shame.
And this can be sin
we've committed
or sin that's
committed against us.
It creates shame.
We see this early
on in Genesis 2,
where God creates our
first parents perfect.
And it says that they were
naked without any what?
Shame.
So, before sin enters
the world, there's no shame.
As soon as they sin,
they cover themselves,
they hide from one another,
and they hide from God.
Do you know what that is?
Shame.
"I don't want God to see me.
I don't want you to see me.
I don't want to be known."
Because intimacy is
"into-me-see,"
and they just
don't want to be seen.
People who are ashamed, they
tend to withdraw, retreat,
hide, or they'll hide
behind, as I said,
a mask or an identity that
they assume and presume,
as an effort of pretending who
they are and defending
the shame they feel.
How many of you feel
shame by what you've done?
How many of you feel shame
by what has been done to you?
You just feel dirty.
Every woman I've ever counseled,
who is a sexual assault victim,
the first thing she did, after
being assaulted, was what?
Take a shower.
I can't remember
a woman who hasn't said,
"And I had to go take a shower."
What is that?
It's that they feel, to use
the language of Genesis 34,
in the story of Dinah,
"defiled," unclean, dirty.
Hebrews 12:1-2,
"Let us also
lay aside every weight."
Is your shame, the sin
committed against you,
does it feel like a weight?
Does it feel like
a taxing burden,
like an emotional anchor?
"And the sin which
clings so closely,"
does it always feel
like it's right there?
"And let us run,"
not just limp, but,
"run with endurance,"
that's perseverance,
keep going, "the race that is
set before us," that God has
purposed for us in our life to
not only heal but to help others
be healed, through Jesus Christ.
Looking to who?
Jesus.
See, if you're just looking
at yourself as a victim,
or just looking at your abuser,
and you're not looking to Jesus,
you're not going
to be able to run.
You're just going to limp for
the rest of your life.
"The founder and perfecter
of our faith,
who for the joy that was
set before him,"
Jesus, though it was painful,
and he shed his tears,
he joyously saved sinners.
He joyously takes shame,
"endured the cross,
despising the--"
What?
"Shame."
We have a God--for those of you
who struggle with the shame of
the sin that's been committed
by you or against you--
we have a God who has come
into human history and has,
of his own volition,
has chosen
to be shamed and victimized.
Jesus was victimized--
emotionally, verbally,
spiritually, physically abused.
He was assaulted.
And he went to the cross,
and he was shamed.
They said horrific things
about his character
that were completely untrue.
He was stripped, altogether--or
almost altogether--naked, I mean,
so shameful for a man.
He was condemned as a criminal.
He was beaten.
He was cursed upon.
He was spit upon.
He was mocked.
He was crucified.
He was shamed.
But the Bible says that
he went to the cross,
despising the shame.
Some of your translations will
say, "scorning the shame."
You sinners need to know that
when Jesus went to the cross,
he took your sin.
You victims need to know,
when Jesus went to the cross,
he took your shame.
And they both died in
the body of Jesus that day.
And so there is forgiveness
of shame--of sin, rather,
and there is taking of shame
in the person and work
of Jesus.
And I really, desperately,
as your pastor,
want you to know and embrace
this great truth,
otherwise, you will feel
forgiven but ashamed,
and you will limp along, rather
than running the race
that is set before you.
And number three, Jesus
cleanses all defilement.
The Bible, between
the Old and New Testament,
has about a dozen words--
defilement, filth, uncleanness--
these are all words
denoting the staining effect
of sin, particularly that
committed against us.
If you read the Old Testament,
and you wonder,
"Why do they have to keep
cleaning their home and have
"cleansing rituals and all of
this mechanism by which to rid
"their homes and their diets,
and their garments of filth
and dirt?"
It's all showing that
sin is like that.
Sin gets into everything,
and it makes it dirty,
and it makes it defiled,
and it makes it disgusting.
And as we labor to keep
our bodies and homes clean,
so Jesus needs to cleanse us
from all of our unrighteousness.
Some of you feel very
defiled, damaged, broken.
And here's what 1 John 1:9 says,
"If we confess
our sins--"
Again, we talk about it with God
and godly, trustworthy people,
beginning with our spouse,
I would hope and pray.
He is what?
"He's faithful."
And I can tell you, from
my life, my wife's life,
and hundreds of people that
we've been able to serve
in varying ways on these
issues over the years,
he is faithful. "--to
forgive us our sins--"
So, whatever sins
you've committed,
Jesus can and will forgive,
if, today, you turn from sin,
trust in him.
"And" to what?
"Cleanse us."
See, the rape victim,
who climbs in the shower,
what they really want is Jesus,
but they just don't know
how to get clean to
the level of the soul,
so they go as far as they can,
which is cleansing of the body.
"To forgive us our sins
and to cleanse us from
all unrighteousness."
And for you victims,
I want you just to memorize,
"cleanse from all
unrighteousness," all of it.
And what that means is you may
even have repressed memories
or disassociation,
and you're doing something,
and all of a sudden
a memory comes back.
And you think, "Man, I thought I
dealt with this, but it's back,
"or it's something I didn't
know, and now I do know."
I talked to a victim,
a woman, not long ago,
and somebody just walked up
behind her and just, it was
a friend that just put a hand on
her shoulder, and she absolutely
fell to the floor weeping
bitterly, did not know why.
It triggered a memory that she
had not remembered in years
of something that had happened
to her, that was assaulting.
And it's cleansing from all
the unrighteousness, all of it.
And the way this works itself
out in the Bible is
symbolic acts.
The people of God are often
told, "Wash your clothes,"
to show what Jesus does.
I want you, every time
you do your laundry,
just to remind yourself
Jesus cleanses
from all unrighteousness.
Every time you do your dishes,
Jesus cleanses
from all unrighteousness.
Every time you sweep
or vacuum the floor,
Jesus cleanses from
all unrighteousness.
This is shown, as well,
in Christian baptism,
that Jesus lived, died,
was buried, and rose.
And as water cleanses
us from filth,
Jesus cleanses us from
all unrighteousness.
As well, in the Bible,
the people of God often wear
what color?
White.
Do you ever wonder why?
It's to show that Jesus cleanses
from all unrighteousness.
So, even the church is typified
in Revelation 19
at the end of the age
as like a bride.
Jesus is like a groom,
and there's this enormous
celebration and wedding feast
that ends human history.
And it says that fine,
white linen, pure and clean,
was given her to wear.
Ladies, it doesn't matter what
you've done
or what's been done to you.
On your wedding day,
you wear what?
You wear white, if
you are in Christ,
because if you are in
Christ, you are clean.
That's your identity.
You're not determined by what
you've done
or what's been done to you.
You're determined by what
Jesus has done for you,
and he cleanses us from
all unrighteousness.
This is why even the people
of God, in the Old Testament,
they would go to the temple.
I've had the privilege
of being there,
at least at the site where
the temple used to reside,
and it's literally
a city on a hill.
It's high and exalted,
and the temple is at the top
of this rock, highly visible.
And there were certain
psalms of ascent,
that the people would sing, as
they would go to worship God
and deal with sin.
And at the base of the mountain,
before they would ascend
to worship God, singing
various psalms of ascent,
they would first stop, and
they would wash their clothes,
and they'd wash their body,
and they'd put on
fresh, white linen, and then
they would go to worship God.
Imagine seeing tens of thousands
of people wearing white.
That's to remind us all:
Jesus cleanses
from all unrighteousness.
For those who are the spouse of
an assault victim,
number one,
God has not given you
an affliction;
he's given you a mission.
Or I should say it this way:
God has not given
us an affliction;
he's given us a mission.
I've got two daughters
that I absolutely
cherish and adore.
And God has daughters that
he cherishes and adores.
And if he would ask some of you
men to marry and love
and serve those women, it is
not an affliction;
it is a mission that
the Father has sent you on,
because he's trusting you
to love his daughter
with his affection.
And in our selfish
moments, we can think,
"This is more difficult
than some might experience.
This is not what I
would've hoped for."
We should, instead, thank God
that he's trusted us with such
a sacred mission and not in any
way view it as an affliction.
Number two, the affection
and the intimacy takes longer,
but it goes deeper, because
for someone who has been hurt,
they will be reticent, cautious
to really trust someone,
even their spouse.
And so it will take longer,
but it will go deeper,
because they will trust you
in a way
they've never trusted anyone
and be vulnerable with you
in a way that has
only been betrayed.
And for those of
you who might ask,
God does not cause
these things to happen,
but he uses them for good.
God does not cause
these things to happen,
but he will use them for good.
And that's why Grace
wrote the chapter.
Father God, as I bring Grace
out, I pray for our church,
that we would be a safe place,
a helpful place,
a healing place.
God, for those who have just
realized that this is their
story, I pray for the time
and energy it's going to take
to process this and trustworthy
people, including their spouse,
to talk about this with.
And, God, it is an epidemic.
It's a growing epidemic, so
we pray against the enemy,
his servants, their
works and effects.
We pray for the power of
the gospel of Jesus Christ
to do its work,
and we pray that
the people of God
would be a means
by which the grace of God
and the love of God is shared.
I thank you for Grace's bravery
and boldness
and her friendship with me.
God, I thank you that
I get to be her husband,
and I pray for the men
in the church, that are single,
that we would not see
them make any victims.
I pray for the men
in the church, who are married,
that they would not
make any victims.
And I pray for the people in
the church, men and women,
who are victims, that they
would know, in Christ,
they are forgiven; in Christ,
their shame is scorned;
and, in Christ, they are clean.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Thank you for
joining me, sweetie.
Rather than doing Q&A today, I
just don't think emotionally
I could handle that,
to be honest with you,
and I didn't want
to expose you
to that kind of situation.
So, thanks for
writing the chapter.
I think you did a great job,
and thanks for being my friend.
Thanks for walking through
this whole process with me.
I would do anything for you.
I would.
Let's start with, how did it
feel for you or what concerns
or apprehensions did you
have once, you know,
we kind of understood
everything,
and then you
started working toward
getting in a Redemption Group,
and talking with people,
and working that through?
What was that like for you?
There was a lot
of fears involved.
I was always
a very private, quiet person,
and so when God
started revealing and
opening my eyes to some of
the things that had been--
had happened to me--it was
a big deal for me
to even share it with you.
And so the thought of continuing
to share that with people for
healing was pretty frightening,
and just to not keep those
things private, and to think
that any healing could possibly
come from more discussion
was confusing to me.
It seemed like you could just
confess it, or talk about it,
and then turn the page, and
you'd be fine, and that was it,
but God had so much more healing
to do in the process
of working it through.
So, as I was entering into
a group with other women,
some who I knew, some who I
didn't really know,
it was a super vulnerable place
for me.
There were many times, where
I wanted to quit and say,
"This is too hard," and that
fear of rejection from people
was big for me.
It's because of lots of
relationships throughout
my life, and so the thought of
telling people this and then
the rejection possibility
that would happen.
And so just sharing and getting
in that group actually was
a healing process, because as
we each shared our story,
and things that had happened,
and different aspects,
it made me realize
that I wasn't alone.
And I knew I wasn't, because
I had the Lord, and I had you,
but there's just something, I
think, for women specifically,
but for all of us in
general, living in community,
it really does help us want to
be strengthened in that journey
of healing, and so just sharing
that--and the women were sharing
their stories, and I couldn't
relate to every detail
of theirs.
They couldn't relate to
every detail of mine,
but there were pieces
in everyone's story,
whether it was shame or just
wanting to suppress the truth,
or embarrassment.
There were lots of different
elements that we could
each relate to in each
other's stories.
And so it just, it was really
helpful to have people
talk through that
in a group setting.
For those who may be
unfamiliar with it,
this is why we started
Redemption Groups,
quite frankly.
We wanted to have a Bible-based,
Jesus-focused, church-connected
way of helping those who
have been abused, addicted,
or have deep hurts and wounds,
and so I know you
brought it out.
Pastor Mike Wilkerson,
who's a friend of mine,
and you're good friends
with his wife, Trisha,
who's been a good friend
to you--he wrote the book,
"Redemption," and it serves
as kind of the basis for our
Redemption Groups, and we really
appreciate them doing that work
for us, and we asked
them to do that,
so that Mars Hill
could be a place that we could
establish groups to help people.
I think over 700 people have
been through Redemption Groups,
and at least that many
in other churches,
as we're hoping to set up
Redemption Groups in other
churches under the leadership
of Pastor Mike and others.
Maybe take a few moments
and explain to people
what a Redemption Group is.
It's different than
a Community Group.
A Community Group meets ongoing
and discusses the content
of the sermon.
Maybe explain Redemption Groups
and how they work with
Community Groups.
Yeah, a Redemption Group
starts out with a weekend
of training and getting to hear
from other leaders and people
who have similar experiences,
and then it goes for about
a quarter every week, and it's
based off the story of Exodus
in the Bible, so it's
a very biblical training,
but it's also very practical.
He talks through deliverance and
how God wants to deliver us from
the slavery of sin, either that
we've committed
or that's been committed
against us.
And then he talks--it talks
through the ransom that God
has already paid, so that we can
experience the next topic
of renewal.
And all those things
are throughout
the Redemption Group training.
You get to continually hear
real stories of people
that have walked through these
painful processes,
and then you break off
into smaller groups,
that they prayerfully
put people into.
They have a leader
and an apprentice
in the group that walk people
through the stories
and how to talk to each other,
not hurt each other
more through comments,
but to receive and love
each other through it,
so it's a very
relational process.
You get to know people that
you knew nothing about before.
And then you continue to just
walk through that process.
And then at the end,
they celebrate,
have a celebration time, just
as Mark has said just to wear
white, you know, celebrate, have
a feast that we get to celebrate
what God has done in
the renewal process,
and not that it's ended
after that quarter--
you will continue, but you
continue under the auspices
of a new identity.
You're not the abuse victim;
you are a renewed
person in Christ,
and he wants to
continue to heal you.
And so the identity
piece is a huge part,
getting rid of the idols and
walking in your new identity
in Christ.
What does it mean for you
that we've got Redemption Groups
at Mars Hill?
Oh, it means the world,
because I know that people
can really experience healing,
and they don't have to be stuck
in shame and the pain of being
a sexual assault victim.
They can help other people,
once they've been trained.
It's just, it's
a continual process for them.
And, yeah, so many people
don't know what to say,
when they hear of
sexual assault stories,
and so this is an essential part
for our church to come in
and love people
who feel unloved.
So, it means the world to me
that we could have
such a resource,
because so many people
didn't know what to say to me,
either.
Yeah.
What counsel would you give for
a spouse, a friend, a parent,
who knows someone that this
is part of their story,
or somebody confides in them
this is part of their story?
What would be helpful for them
to say and do and unhelpful
for them to say and do?
Well, I think praying for
them, being a good listener,
being someone they can
trust, a confidante,
not someone who's going to go
and spread what they've confided
in you, just to remind them
of God's love for them,
to remind them of his desire
for healing and renewal,
and to cleanse from
all unrighteousness.
I needed to be reminded
of those things regularly,
because as new memories or lies
try to invade
during the healing process,
the truth needs to be spoken,
and not in a just an aloof way
or unfeeling way,
but a way that is genuine,
and even just
hugging the person,
if they're okay with that, if
it's someone that's, you know,
a girlfriend to another
gal, or your wife.
I think those are just important
ways to really help that person
see that you do care.
And if they need help, help
them into a Redemption Group.
Help them into a community
that's trusting
or a biblical counselor,
if you're not
in the Mars Hill community,
praying with them,
praying over them,
checking in on them to make sure
that they're okay
in the healing process.
I had many friends that just
regularly would text me or call
and say, you know, "How
can I pray for you today?
What is your struggle today?"
And they would just
pray for me right then,
and they would pray for
me throughout the weeks.
Just not rejecting me was huge.
And then, yeah, just
being good listeners.
I think I'm going
to end it there.
I don't think
I can do any more.
We're going to
transition at this point.
We'll collect our offering, and
that is to forward the ministry
of Jesus, and we want
people to get help.
Since we've recently grown
by 5,000 people in 2 weeks,
we have
a whole lot of people to help,
and so we appreciate
your support,
prayerfully and financially.
If you're new or want
to get connected,
give us that visitor card,
because we really want to follow
up with you and do anything
we can to connect to you.
So, if you put that
in the offering,
that'll enable us to serve you.
We'll take Communion, which is
remembering the broken body
and shed blood of Jesus.
The blood of Jesus cleanses
from all unrighteousness.
And as you take Communion,
you're publicly saying,
"He died, so that I could
be forgiven and cleansed."
And it's a very powerful public
identification with Jesus.
And, lastly,
we're going to sing.
And singing for us, today,
is a way of praying.
It's working out what the heart
is feeling, through the voice.
And so, as we sing, we're
praying collectively
as the people of God, today,
some praying
and grieving for ourselves,
and some for those we
know and love, or some for both.
And so, yeah, sweetie,
if you'd be willing,
maybe just close
our time in prayer.
I'd appreciate that.
Lord, thank you.
Thank you for giving me
the strength to write this story
that you are still weaving
and playing out in my life.
Thank you that you are taking
it to help other people,
and I pray that you'd
continue to do that.
I pray that men and women who
have sexual assault in their
history, Lord, that they would
just move toward the release
from the shackles that
it causes for them.
Lord, I pray
against the enemy's lies
and division of community
for them.
Lord, I pray that
they would trust you
as their Heavenly Father,
to be their source for
their identity, and their joy,
and their healing.
Lord, I thank you that you don't
let us just continue
broken and unhealed, that you
desire so much more.
And so I pray for that path
for all of us, in Jesus' name.
Thanks.